JAVA TRAINEE

Summary

2.5 years of experience in Java / J2EE software development including Analysis, designing and development of enterprise application. Exposure to all phases of Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) and also AGILE methodology. Extensive experience in design and development of multitier application using Java, J2EE, JSP, JSF, Servlets, Spring. Experience in client side technologies such as HTML, DHTML, CSS, JSP, JSF, JavaScript, AJAX. Proficient in Oracle Database and programming using SQL, PL/SQL. Good working knowledge of Apache Tomcat and Glass Fish 4.1 Application servers. Excellent knowledge of using Eclipse IDE and Net Beans IDE. Excellent communication and interpersonal skills and involved in client interaction, status reports. Proficient in using OOPs Concepts (Polymorphism, Inheritance, Encapsulation) Overloading & Overriding, Finally, Finalize, Garbage collection, Synchronization, Collections, Arrays, Interfaces, Multithreading etc., Used Design Patterns like MVC (Model-View-Controller) and Singleton, Factory, Value Object etc. Highlights

SOFTWARE SKILLS Design Skills and tools: UML, Object Oriented Analysis and Design (OOAD), Design patterns (Singleton, Business Delegate, IOC, DAO, SDLC,). Java: Object Oriented Programming (OOP), Data Structure, Collections Framework, Exception Handling, Java I/O etc J2EE: J2EE (JSP, JSF, Servlets, EJB). Open Source Frameworks: Spring Framework, Spring MVC, Spring IOC, JDBC. Web/Application Servers & Middleware: Apache Tomcat, Glass Fish 4.1. Database tools: SQL, PL/SQL, Oracle, MySQL. IDE: Eclipse, Net Beans. Source Control: CVS. Software Application Tools: Poseidon (UML Modeling), Crystal Clear (Report generation). Other languages: VB, C#, ASP.NET.

Experience

11/2010 to 11/2012 Bickford Senior Living Burlington, IA

- Description: Four-Soft Ltd now known as Kewill is a leading provider of multimodal transportation and logistics software provider for seamless supply chain execution. Nov 2010 - Apr 2012 Description: It handles all the different phases of logistics starting from Warehouse Management, Transportation, Trade, Customs and Trade compliance. Responsibilities:
- Improved the development process by delivering innovative ideas in design review and code review activities of the team
- Developed DAO for communicating with the database.
- Defined business facades to handle multiple calls to the DAO 's. Defined custom exceptions at business layer and DAO layer. Use of core java, which includes Collections.
- Responsible to enhance the Portal UI using HTML, Java Script, XML, JSP, Java, CSS as per the requirements and providing the client side Java script validations and Server side Bean Validation Framework.
- Understanding the client requirements from status meetings and maintaining the UI as per the client needs.
- Used SQL Developer to write the SQL queries.
- Handled production issues on timely manner.
- Designed and formatted all the reports throughout the application using Crystal Clear(Report generation tool)
- Involved in Unit, integration and QA testing. Apr 2012 July 2012 Description: To avoid redundancy of data MDM stores the common data required by all application in its database and makes the user to modify the data in MDM and then forwards the modified data to all the applications connected to it. Responsibilities:
- Designed and implemented are Country, Party(Information regarding Customers, Vendors, Suppliers is stored here), Product Activation (Based on the admin selection of products in MDM the user gets access to MDM data) and User Profile (Basic information of the user is stored in this module instead of keeping the same data in individual applications)
- Developed/Customized the GUI based on client request using technologies like HTML, JavaScript, AJAX.
- Provide knowledge sharing session to team members to better understand the company framework, product functionality, coding structure, design approach and speed up the development process.
- Report to R&D department for any issues of fixes in the framework.
- Handle production issues. Description: An application that finds the best possible path from a beginning location to a destination location provided based on factors such as shortest path, cost effectiveness and time dependency. Responsibilities:
- Designed and implemented Transport Order (Selection of the source and destination for the shipment)
- Designed Rate and Contract (Contains a set of rates a for a shipment contract from one location to another)
- Developed/Customized the GUI based on client request using technologies like HTML, JavaScript, AJAX.
- Programmed the algorithm for finding the best possible path using PL/SQL(procedure).
- Report to R&D department for any issues of fixes in the framework.
- Handle production issues.
- Designed the database using Poseidon.

Java Trainee 06/2010 to 10/2012 Challenger School Los Altos, CA

- Description: CMC Ltd is a leading system engineering and integration company in India. It's expertise lye in product development, Software solution, Infrastructure management including cloud, mobility and virtualization, Embedded and Real Time system. Responsibilities:
- Design and develop basic applications such as student management system, Hospital management system.
- Design the database structure using Poseidon.
- Unit test the application and handle bugs.
- Integration testing of application design and developed by others and raise issues in the application.

Teaching Assistant 01/2014 to 12/2014 University Of Houston City, STATE

- Responsibilities:
- TA for course Internet Application Development where in had to assist student in understanding the assignment and implementing that in C#,

ASP.NET

• TA for course Excel and Access where in had to clear students doubts, general or pertaining to the assignment.

Education

Master of Science: Management Information Systems University of Houston City, State, US Master of Science in Management Information Systems. Aug 2015 University of Houston - Clear Lake, Houston, TX

Bachelor of Engineering: Information Technology Muffakham Jah College of Engineering and Technology, Osmania University City, State, IN Bachelor of Engineering in Information Technology May 2010 Muffakham Jah College of Engineering and Technology, Osmania University, Hyderabad, India

Certifications

Java Programmer (CMC LTD.) Software Engineer (Four - Soft LTD)

Skills

Database, Integration, Integrator, Java, Testing, Logistics, Application Design, Assay System, Infrastructure Management, Integration Testing, Real Time, System Engineering, Unit Test, Virtualization, Html, Engineer, Kewill, Long-term Disability, Ltd, Software Engineer, Sql, Supply Chain, Collections, Credit, Css, Design Review, Exceptions, Jsp, Qa, Qa Testing, Ui, User Interface, Warehouse Management, Xml, Access, Application Development, Asp, Asp.net, C#, Excel, Ms Asp, Teaching, Ajax, Graphical User Interface, Gui, Javascript, Algorithm, Pl/sql, Cmc, Analysis Design, Apache, Client Interaction, Collection, Cvs, Data Structure, Design Patterns, Dhtml, Eclipse, Ejb, Enterprise Application, Frameworks, Garbage Collection, J2ee, Jdbc, Jsf, Life Cycle, Middleware, Model View Controller, Model-view-controller, Mvc, Mysql, Object Oriented, Object Oriented Analysis, Object Oriented Programming, Ooad, Oop, Open Source, Oracle, Sdlc, Servlets, Software Development, Software Development Life Cycle, Structured Software, Tomcat, Uml, Uml Modeling, Coding, Its, Master Data Management, Mdm